<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[What did I get myself into???]]></title>
  <link href="http://rodriguezd.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rodriguezd.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-28T23:09:17-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://rodriguezd.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Rodriguez]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[davidrodriguez212@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So at the end of Day 1 ...]]></title>
    <link href="http://rodriguezd.github.com/blog/2013/03/28/so-at-the-end-of-day-1-dot-dot-dot/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-28T22:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rodriguezd.github.com/blog/2013/03/28/so-at-the-end-of-day-1-dot-dot-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Don&#8217;t you hate it when at the end of a long day, whatever that means for you, you ask yourself &#8220;So what did I really get done today?&#8221; and then the mental math just doesn&#8217;t seem to add up? I know I can be really hard on myself and I know that I got more done than I give myself credit for but I just wish I thought &#8220;I did too much today.&#8221; more often.</p>

<p>So I started the day finishing one Code School course and then starting another. Three videos in all and the accompanying exercises for each. If you&#8217;re not familiar with Code School courses, each course consists of about five to seven, five to fifteen minute videos each followed by eight to ten practice problems. I have a habit of pausing the videos often to look up associated material in an effort to understand the topic better. Needless to say, this can really slow things down. But then maybe I get more bang for my time buck. I just need to not get carried away.</p>

<p>Then while eating my tuna melt with chips for lunch, I decided to look up information about the Twitter API. I had no intention of this going beyond the last chip on my plate. So much for intentions. About three hours later I was still experimenting on IRB with the Twitter API via the &#8216;Twitter&#8217; Ruby gem (after about an hour of troubleshooting) and the Foursquare API via their developer site. What I was most curious about was what data one could access and what form did it take. At the end of it all, I decided that I will not pursue the Twitter API becuase of the limitations they place on the public API. I concluded it would become a problem. Foursquare looks more promising even if I may wind up duplicating some functionality that already exists on their site. But then the end goal is learning new things and practicing coding so whatever.</p>

<p>So I never got to working on the &#8220;fundraise&#8221; app today as I intended but then I did research the APIs pretty thoroughly which I would have done later. So I guess I can call it a draw.</p>

<p>Tomorrow I will finish that second Code School course, get in some <em>Eloquent Ruby</em> reading, but then the rest of the day is all about &#8220;fundraise&#8221;. It&#8217;s been a good while since I&#8217;ve spent so much time in one day working on dev stuff. It felt good but I have to be smarter about it. I will be tomorrow.</p>

<p>&#8220;<em>Pick your battles big enough to matter, small enough to win.</em>&#8221; - Jonathan Kozol</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring Break => Code, Code, Read, Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://rodriguezd.github.com/blog/2013/03/28/spring-break-equals-%3E-code/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-28T09:04:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rodriguezd.github.com/blog/2013/03/28/spring-break-equals->-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is the first day of my school&#8217;s Spring break. I&#8217;m off until April 7th. Now is when I have to stop thinking and talking about all the great stuff I&#8217;m going to get done over the break and start actually doing it. So here&#8217;s my Spring break checklist:</p>

<ul>
<li>Get my &#8220;fundraise&#8221; Rails app into presentable shape and deploy it to Heroku</li>
<li>Create a Sinatra app that utilizes either the Twitter or 4Squre API (OR a Rails app that catalogs, retrieves, and displays photo image files based on their embedded EXIF data)</li>
<li>Start writing tests using Rspec for everything!</li>
<li>Watch one Code School video each day (Rails, Javascript, GIT)</li>
<li>Finish reading <em>Eloquent Ruby</em></li>
<li>Finish reading <em>Pragmatic Thinking &amp; Learning</em></li>
<li>Revisit my HTML tutorial book to prep for learning Javascript</li>
<li>Finish my income taxes (Always sucks. Times a million when you owe like my sorry ass.)</li>
</ul>


<p>Yeah. That&#8217;s it.</p>

<p>And of course blogging about my progress along the way. (I&#8217;ll try to keep the cursing to a minimum.)</p>

<p>&#8220;<em>Getting good at something means going through various periods of being not-good, during which you tend to feel dumb, clueless, incompetent.</em>&#8221; - <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/erikaandersen/2013/03/09/the-secret-to-getting-really-really-good-at-something/">Erika Andersen</a>, <em>Forbes</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So where do I begin?]]></title>
    <link href="http://rodriguezd.github.com/blog/2013/03/21/so-where-do-i-begin/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-21T21:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rodriguezd.github.com/blog/2013/03/21/so-where-do-i-begin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3><em>A long time ago, in a galaxy far, far, away &#8230;</em></h3>

<p>I&#8217;ve been meaning to start blogging for quite some time. But like most who do, I just hadn&#8217;t gotten around to it. My time has come.</p>

<p>What you&#8217;re reading now was not my first draft of this post. In what I can only describe as an episode of irrational post writing exuberance, I began writing a rambling post that began with my childhood career preferences. It went downhill from there. Luckily for me and every reader of my blog, my wonderful and beautiful girlfriend (a.k.a my fiance) knocked some blogging sense into me. (She&#8217;s a budding food blogger herself. <a href="http://foodentity.wordpress.com">Check hers out</a>.)</p>

<p>So let&#8217;s just say that about a year ago I started down a path to change my career from a high school math teacher to a full stack web developer. Being a teacher is not a lifetime occupation for me, it&#8217;s not where I&#8217;m meant to be. It had it&#8217;s moments, there are many things I did that I am very proud of, and in one very significant and wonderful way it lead to very big change in my life for the better. I have no regrets but it&#8217;s time to move on.</p>

<p>I have an engineering degree, I used to work for Fortune 100 companies on technology projects, and I have always been the techie, tinkering type. How I wound up teaching is not important. What is important is that I have decided to go back to where I belong. Back to the world of technology, engineering, and problem solving with creative solutions. (In other words, working on really cool stuff, using really cool technologies, with really cool people, and making magic happen.)</p>

<p>So in posts to follow I hope to chronicle my experiences on this &#8220;little&#8221; endeavor I have embarked on. I am also quite sure there will be a decent peppering of tangential and completely random posts on events, people, and thoughts the universe throws my way. I can&#8217;t tell you what to expect should you choose to return and read my future posts because frankly I have no idea what to expect myself. We can find out together. Stay tuned.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s gonna be interesting.</p>

<p>&#8220;<em>And, when you want something, all the universe conspires in helping you to achieve it.</em>&#8221; - Paulo Coelho, <em>The Alchemist</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
